
<section>
  <title>Use SVN and let your users know about it</title>
  <para>
    (Hopefully) All OCaml-related Debian packages are maintained using a
    centralized <ulink url="http://subversion.tigris.org/">Subversion</ulink>
    (<acronym>SVN</acronym> for short) repository. This practice reduce the
    efforts needed to contribute work inside &ocaml-force; and, in case of
    need, provides a place where to massively perform changes to all
    OCaml-related Debian packages.
  </para>
  <para>
    Nonetheless, Debian users can benefit knowing we are using a SVN
    repository (they can for instance subscribe to the RSS feed for changes
    or have a place where to look for finding patches corresponding to bugs
    tagged "pending" in the BTS).
  </para>
  <para>
    For this reason <emphasis>it is recommended to add the
    <code>XS-X-Vcs-Svn</code> field to the <filename>debian/control</filename>
    of packages maintained in &ocaml-force; SVN repository</emphasis>. Its name
  specifies that we are using Subversion as our Version Control System
  (<acronym>VCS</acronym>); its value is the URL pointing to the package's
  trunk directory.
  </para>
  <para>
    The general scheme for using the field is thus:
    <programlisting>
  XS-X-Vcs-Svn: svn://svn.debian.org/svn/pkg-ocaml-maint/trunk/packages/<emphasis>PACKAGE_NAME</emphasis>
    </programlisting>
    <example>
      <title>Usage example of the XS-X-Vcs-Svn field, from the
        <application>findlib</application> package
      </title>
      <programlisting>
  Source: findlib
  Section: devel
  Priority: optional
  Maintainer: Stefano Zacchiroli &lt;zack@debian.org&gt;
  Build-Depends: debhelper (>> 4.0.0), ocaml (>= 3.09.2), m4, gawk | awk, dpatch, cdbs
  Standards-Version: 3.7.2
  <emphasis>XS-X-Vcs-Svn: svn://svn.debian.org/svn/pkg-ocaml-maint/trunk/packages/findlib</emphasis>

  Package: ocaml-findlib
  Section: devel
  Architecture: any
  Depends: ocaml-nox-${F:OCamlABI}, ${shlibs:Depends}, ${misc:Depends}
  Description: Management tool for OCaml programming language libraries
  ...
      </programlisting>
    </example>
  </para>
</section>

<section>
    <title>How to obtain a copy of the SVN repository</title>
    <para>
      You can obtain a copy of debian-ocaml-maint SVN repository by
      <programlisting>
  svn co svn+ssh://svn.debian.org/svn/pkg-ocaml-maint
      </programlisting>
      You must be member of the
      <ulink url="http://pkg-ocaml-maint.alioth.debian.org/">Debian
      OCaml Task Force</ulink> in order to have write access to the repository. 
    </para>
</section>

<section>
    <title>Structure of the SVN repository</title>
    <para>
        We keep all files of the debian subdirectory under SVN control, and
        upstream only as a compressed tarball. The rationale behind this is
        that changes to upstream files should be managed by the <application>dpatch</application> patch
        manager. Hence, all the diffs to upstream files are kept in a
        subdirectory of <filename>debian/</filename>, and it is not necessary to manage upstream on
        file-by-file basis.
    </para>

    <para>
        The structure of the pkg-ocaml-maint SVN repository is as follows, where
        generic names are indicated in square brackets <varname>[ .. ]</varname>, and where the
        contents of subdirectories not directly relevant for package management
        are not detailed:
        <programlisting>
 tags
   packages
     [package1]
       [version1]
       [version2]
       ...
     [package2]
       [version1]
       ...
     ...
   projects
 test
 trunk
   packages
     [package1]
       trunk
         debian
       upstream
         [upstream-tarball-version1]
         [upstream-tarball-version2]
         ...
     [package2]
     ...
   policy
   projects
   tools
        </programlisting>
    </para>
</section>

<section>
    <title>How to add a new package to the SVN repository</title>
    <para>
        Place yourself in the directory <filename>trunk/packages</filename> of your working copy of
        the SVN repository. Create a directory with the same name as your
        source package (let's say, my-package), and subdirectories <filename>upstream</filename>
        and <filename>trunk</filename>.  Put the current upstream tarball in <filename>upstream</filename>, and the
        current debian directory with all its relevant files in <filename>trunk</filename>. This
        should now look like this:
        <programlisting>
 trunk/packages/my_package
   upstream
     my_package_1.2.3.orig.tar.gz
   trunk
     debian
       changelog
       control
       copyright
       patches
         00_list
         01_patch1.dpatch
         ...
       ...
       </programlisting>
   </para>

   <para>
       If everything is in order you can do a <command>svn add my_package</command> from the <filename>trunk/packages</filename> directory, and eventually <command>svn commit</command>.
    </para>
</section>

<section>
    <title>How to set up your package for use with <application>svn-buildpackage</application></title>

    <para>
        Please see the <application>svn-buildpackage</application> documentation for complete
        information. The important issues here are:
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Since we keep upstream as a tarball we have to use <application>svn-buildpackage</application> in
                    so-called merge mode. This means that, before compiling the package,
                    the debianized source tree is constructed by untarring the orig tarball, and then merging the contents of the trunk subdirectory in it.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The structure of our SVN repository is not among the default structures
                    of <application>svn-buildpackage</application>. Hence, we have to override the default location of some
                    directories.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
        Place yourself in <filename>trunk/packages/my_packages/trunk</filename>, and do the following:
        <command>svn propset mergeWithUpstream 1 debian</command>.
        This registers the property "mergeWithUpstream" with the current
	directory, such that <application>svn-buildpackage</application> knows
	that it has to use merge mode as explained above.
    </para>

    <para>
        Create a file <filename>debian/svn-deblayout</filename> with the following contents:
        <programlisting>
origDir=../upstream
origUrl=svn+ssh://svn.debian.org/svn/pkg-ocaml-maint/trunk/packages/my_package/upstream
tagsUrl=svn+ssh://svn.debian.org/svn/pkg-ocaml-maint/tags/packages/my_package
        </programlisting>
    </para>

    <para>
        Remember that "my_package" has to be replaced by the name of your
        actual package. <application>svn-buildpackage</application> will not include this file in the
        source package when actually building the package.
    </para>

    <para>
        If you tried <application>svn-buildpackage</application> before writing your <filename>debian/svn-deblayout</filename> remember
        to delete <filename>.svn/deb-layout</filename>, since <application>svn-buildpackages</application> caches here the content
        of <filename>svn-deblayout</filename> (that would be empty in this case) and will ignore
        your <filename>debian/svn-deblayout</filename>.
    </para>
</section>

<section>
    <title>How to build a package with <application>svn-buildpackage</application></title>

    <para>
        Please refer to the <application>svn-builpackage</application> documentation for more complete
        information. Here is just a quick guide.
    </para>

    <para>
        All options, except those starting on <option>--svn</option>, are passed to
        <application>dpkg-buildpackage</application>. Hence, basic usage should be something like this
        (from the <filename>trunk/packages/my_package/trunk</filename> directory): <command>svn-buildpackage -rfakeroot -uc -us</command>.
    </para>

    <para>
      <application>svn-buildpackage</application> will complain when your copy
      of the debian directory is not in sync with the repository. You may use
      the option <option>--svn-ignore-new</option> to override this behaviour.
      The package will be build in the directory
      <filename>../build-area</filename>.
    </para>

    <para>
        If your package is ready for upload you may use the <option>--svn-tag</option> option
        for the final build. This will put a tag in the svn-repository on the
        current version, and add a new entry in the changlog to start working
        on the upcomming next version: <command>svn-buildpackage --svn-tag</command>.
        Provided you have commited all your changes to the svn repository, this
        will after a successful build of the package create a tag for the current
        version in <filename>tags/packages/my_package</filename>. The tagging is done directly in the
        SVN repository.
    </para>

    <tip>
        <para>
	  Some useful aliases taken from the
	  <application>svn-buildpackage</application> HOWTO:
            <programlisting>
alias svn-b='svn-buildpackage -rfakeroot --svn-dont-clean -us -uc --svn-ignore'
alias svn-bt='svn-buildpackage -rfakeroot --svn-lintian --svn-dont-clean --svn-tag'
            </programlisting>
        </para>

        <para>
            The former (<command>svn-b</command>) is to be used for test builds, while you are
            working on your package; while the latter (<command>svn-bt</command>) is to be used at
            the end, after you commit your changes and just before uploading a new
            version of the package to the debian archive.
        </para>

        <para>
            Adding -k&lt;your gpg id&gt; to the svn-bt alias may also be useful when working on
            collaboratively maintained packages:
            <programlisting>
alias svn-bt='svn-buildpackage -rfakeroot -k&lt;gpgid&gt; --svn-lintian --svn-dont-clean --svn-tag'
            </programlisting>
        </para>
    </tip>
</section>

<section>
    <title>dpatch</title>

    <para>
        dpatch will work properly at package build time with the SVN
        structure described above since all of the build process will be
        carried out in a fresh directory. However, invoking
        <filename>debian/rules</filename> with the "clean" target in
        the <filename>trunk/</filename> directory will fail since
        dpatch is unable to de-apply patches. Passing
        <option>--svn-dont-clean</option> to
        <application>svn-buildpackage</application> fixes this
        misbehaviour (aliases suggested above already include this
        flag).  </para>

    <para>
        If you want to use dpatch-edit-patch to handle patches, you will need to invoke
        it in "debian only mode" (<option>-b</option> flag, see man dpatch-edit-patch) and to tell him
        where to find the upstream tarball. Adding the following line to your
        <filename>~/.dpatch.conf</filename> will be enough:
        <programlisting>
conf_origtargzpath=../upstream
        </programlisting>
    </para>
</section>

