<para>
  To help maintainers of OCaml-related packages in adhering to this policy, a
  class for the <ulink url="http://build-common.alioth.debian.org/">CDBS
    build system</ulink> has been made available and is shipped as part of
  the <filename>ocaml-nox</filename> package. Please consider using it in your
  packages at it will both ease your work and permit to perform changes to a
  wide range of packages acting on a single piece of software (the CDBS class
  itself).
</para>

<para>
  To use the class in your package it is enough to include the file
  <filename>/usr/share/cdbs/1/class/ocaml.mk</filename> from your
  <filename>debian/rules</filename>. If you use debhelper (please do) you
  should include the OCaml class after the debhelper on. A typical
  <filename>debian/rules</filename> heading for a package using plain Makefile
  (i.e. no autotools) and dpatch is as follows:
  <programlisting>
#!/usr/bin/make -f
include /usr/share/cdbs/1/rules/debhelper.mk
include /usr/share/cdbs/1/class/makefile.mk
include /usr/share/cdbs/1/class/ocaml.mk
include /usr/share/cdbs/1/rules/dpatch.mk
  </programlisting>
  For an example of such a package see the <filename>pcre-ocaml</filename>
  Debian source package.
</para>

<para>
  A detailed description of how to use the OCaml CDBS class should be provided
  in this section, but at the time of writing is a future work :-). In the
  meantime if you know CDBS, the .mk files which compose the OCaml
  class are well commented and they should give you enough information to
  customize the build process of your package. The latest version of them is
  available in the repository of the &ocaml-force; and can be browsed on the
  web:
  <variablelist>

    <varlistentry>
      <term><filename><ulink url="http://git.debian.org/?p=pkg-ocaml-maint/packages/ocaml.git;a=blob;f=debian/cdbs/ocaml-vars.mk;hb=HEAD">ocaml-vars.mk</ulink></filename></term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  contains (Makefile) convenience variables which can be used in
	  <filename>debian/rules</filename>
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
      
    <varlistentry>
      <term><filename><ulink url="http://git.debian.org/?p=pkg-ocaml-maint/packages/ocaml.git;a=blob;f=debian/cdbs/ocaml.mk;hb=HEAD">ocaml.mk</ulink></filename></term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  implements the class logic
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
      
  </variablelist>
</para>
